A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests, Series E FA314
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Organizations and Parks
  - Organizations and Parks - Miscellaneous - United States Historical Society, 1923-1946 (Box 46, Folder 457)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave pictures to Pocantico School.
  - Organizations and Parks - Miscellaneous - Horticultural Society of New York, 1930-1961 (Box 46, Folder 458)
    Mary French Rockefeller a member; comments on Rockefeller Center flower displays.
  - Organizations and Parks - Miscellaneous - United States Flag Association, 1930-1950 (Box 46, Folder 459)
    Patriotic organization; no Rockefeller interest.
  - Organizations and Parks - Miscellaneous - National Wildlife Federation, 1947-1961 (Box 46, Folder 460)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. purchased some stamps; most appeals declined.
  - Organizations and Parks - Miscellaneous - Save-A-Life League, 1918-1956 (Box 46, Folder 461)
  - Organizations and Parks - Miscellaneous - New York Letter Carriers' Association, 1922-1961 (Box 46, Folder 462)
    Annual Contributions to sick and death benefits association, by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and office.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Historical Association, 1925-1958 (Box 46, Folder 463)
    A. Beveridge and G. Ford ask John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to contribute, 1925; declined. In 1927, $10,000 given for study of national and linguistic origins in America of 1790. No later requests or contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., A. Beveridge, Thomas B. Appleget.
    169A2
  - Organizations and Parks - American Association for Medical Progress, 1924-1928 (Box 46, Folder 464)
    Society of laymen endorsing medical research, primarily vivisection. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined to join, but gave $7,800, 1925-1928. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Thomas B. Appleget.
    169A3
  - Organizations and Parks - Arbitration Society of America, 1922-1925 (Box 46, Folder 465)
    To foster and organize tribunal to handle controversies which are questions of fact rather than matters of law, to ease court congestions. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $2,500. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Raymond B. Fosdick.
    169A4
  - Organizations and Parks - American Arbitration Association, 1926-1959 (Box 46, Folder 466)
    Consolidation of several arbitration organizations. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest stemmed from activities in Chamber of Commerce; he made regular small contributions until 1942. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Arthur Woods, Dana S. Creel.
    169A41
  - Organizations and Parks - American Arbitration Association - Inter-American Commercial Commission, 1939-1948 (Box 47, Folder 467)
    Commercial arbitration, principally between the nationals of various American states. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $42,000. Relation to Chamber of Commerce. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169A411
  - Organizations and Parks - American Planning and Civic Association, 1929-1960 (Box 47, Folder 468)
    Organized to cultivate high ideals of civic life and beauty in America, and improve landscape. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave to budget. Cooperation with National Park Service. Abby Aldrich Rockefeller 1935 gift to improve highway landscapes; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. interest in work of Association. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Arthur Woods, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Horace Albright.
    169A5
  - Organizations and Parks - American Planning and Civic Association - Contributions, 1940-1960 (Box 47, Folder 469)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller contribution toward roadside landscaping; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. annual gifts; contributions by Laurance S. Rockefeller and Rockefeller Brothers Fund. Correspondents include Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Planning and Civic Association - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1939-1961 (Box 47, Folder 470)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller became member of Board of Directors, 1951, but no initiative was taken by the Rockefeller office in the Association's affairs. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Carl O. Gustafson.
    Open per KWR 02/14/2006.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Planning and Civic Association - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1939-1961 (Box 47, Folder 0470A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Planning and Civic Association - Laurance S. Rockefeller - Contributions, 1939-1961 (Box 47, Folder 471)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller's annual dues and occasional special gifts.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Planning and Civic Association - Laurance S. Rockefeller - Minutes, 1959-1961 (Box 47, Folder 472)
    Copies of minutes sent to Laurance S. Rockefeller as trustee.
  - Organizations and Parks - Society of Arts and Crafts, Boston, 1925-1929 (Box 47, Folder 473)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. lent $9,000, written off as bad debt, to society seeking to encourage arts by providing market for display and sale of art objects. Correspondents include W. T. Aldrich, Willard S. Richardson, Charles O. Heydt.
    169A51
  - Organizations and Parks - National Alliance of Art and Industry (Art Center), 1921-1938 (Box 47, Folder 474)
    Plan to provide market for artists' products. In 1929, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $10,000 for three years to employ a director. From 1929-1933, he gave $70,000. Correspondents include Welles Bosworth, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    169A52
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, 1940-June 1956 (Box 47, Folder 475)
    Appeals for aid or interest declined. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $50 to buy cigars for Sibelius, 1951. Nelson A. Rockefeller contribution to Institute of Contemporary Art, 1956. Mary French Rockefeller contributions to Village Art Center. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    169A6
    Open per KWR 02/14/2006. Closed material separated to Folder 475A.
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, 1940-June 1956 (Box 47, Folder 0475A)
    David Rockefeller contribution to Cleveland Museum of Art, 1956. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, July 1956-July 1959 (Box 48, Folder 476)
    Appeals for aid or interest declined. Nelson A. Rockefeller contribution to Institute of Contemporary Art, 1956. Mary French Rockefeller contributions to Village Art Center. Laurance S. Rockefeller contribution to Lemuel Ayers Gallery, 1958. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, July 1956-July 1959 (Box 48, Folder 0476A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, September 1959-1960 (Box 48, Folder 477)
    Appeals for aid or interest declined. Mary French Rockefeller contributions to Village Art Center. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, September 1959-1960 (Box 48, Folder 0477A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, 1961, 1963 (Box 48, Folder 478)
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations, 1961, 1963 (Box 48, Folder 0478A)
    David Rockefeller gift to Arkansas Art Center, 1961. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations - Institute of Contemporary Art, 1951-1961 (Box 48, Folder 479)
  - Organizations and Parks - Art Organizations - Institute of Contemporary Art, 1951-1961 (Box 48, Folder 0479A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Archaeological Survey of Asia Minor, 1923-1931 (Box 48, Folder 480)
    In 1923, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $,5000 to investigate potential value of Anatolia ruins studies. In 1926-1927, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $9,000. Correspondents include W. H. Buckler, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Organizations and Parks - Deissman Excavations at Ephesus, 1925-1946 (Box 48, Folder 481)
    From 1926-1928, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $31,000 to very productive work of Austrian and German excavations at Ephesus. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169A61
  - Organizations and Parks - Rhode Island League for Arts and Crafts - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Interest, 1938-1940 (Box 48, Folder 482)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller made small contribution to organization assisting in the development of native crafts in Rhode Island. Correspondents include Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    169A62
  - Organizations and Parks - Sculptors Guild, Inc., 1938-1961 (Box 48, Folder 483)
    Small gifts by Mary French Rockefeller; one $1,000 gift by Laurance S. Rockefeller. Correspondents include Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller.
    169A63
  - Organizations and Parks - Artists' Gallery, 1938-1961 (Box 48, Folder 484)
    Small contributions by various family members; no real family interest. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    169A64
  - Organizations and Parks - American Institute of Decorators, 1941-1960 (Box 48, Folder 485)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. an honorary member; no active interest in organization. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169A65
  - Organizations and Parks - American Federation of Arts, 1932-1961 (Box 49, Folder 486)
    Declinations of requests to accept positions in Federation; small irregular family contributions. Correspondents include Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Mary French Rockefeller.
    169A66
  - Organizations and Parks - American Federation of Arts, 1932-1961 (Box 49, Folder 0486A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Association for the Protection of the Adirondacks, 1902-1936 (Box 49, Folder 487)
    Organization lobbied for protection of New York forests. John D. Rockefeller a life member, but no active Rockefeller participation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller.
    169A8
  - Organizations and Parks - African-American Institute, 1956-1962 (Box 49, Folder 488)
    Dana S. Creel a director of Institute. Contributions. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel.
  - Organizations and Parks - African-American Institute, 1956-1962 (Box 49, Folder 488A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material.
    David Rockefeller contributions to African Student Union, 1956, and to Institute's African Leader program, 1959. Other contributions. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - Academy of American Poets, 1936-1961 (Box 49, Folder 489)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd contributions; no real family interest in organization. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller.
    169Ac
    Folder 489A reviewed by KWR, 05/12/2010. Previously restricted items were reintegrated into Folder 489.
  - Organizations and Parks - Albert Schweitzer Fellowship, Inc., 1949-1960 (Box 49, Folder 490)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller contribution to hospital. Other appeals from various groups trading in on Schweitzer's name declined. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
    169Al
  - Organizations and Parks - Albert Schweitzer Fellowship, Inc., 1949-1960 (Box 49, Folder 0490A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Forestry Association, 1917-1933 (Box 49, Folder 491)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave toward education work for preservation of forests; Laurance S. Rockefeller contribution to budget, 1958. Other appeals declined. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169Am
  - Organizations and Parks - American Forestry Association, 1934-1961 (Box 49, Folder 492)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Forestry Association, 1934-1961 (Box 49, Folder 0492A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Forestry Association - Contributions, 1919-1956 (Box 49, Folder 493)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Craftsmens Cooperative Council, Inc., 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 494)
    Occupational therapy for returning veterans. Contributions by Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller.
    169Am2
  - Organizations and Parks - American Geographical Society, 1924-1961 (Box 50, Folder 495)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $4,500 toward cost of Brazilian expedition which became lost in the Amazon country. Other appeals declined. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169Am3
  - Organizations and Parks - American Geographical Society, 1924-1961 (Box 50, Folder 0495A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Geographical Society - Laurance S. Rockefeller Membership, 1935, 1951-1960 (Box 50, Folder 496)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller a life member.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Heritage Foundation, 1947-1955 (Box 50, Folder 497)
    Organized to reawaken patriotism in America. Sponsored Freedom Train, drives to bring out the electorate; supported Radio Free Europe through Crusade for Freedom. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Winthrop Aldrich.
    169Am4
  - Organizations and Parks - American Heritage Foundation, 1956-1961 (Box 50, Folder 498)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Heritage Foundation, 1956-1961 (Box 50, Folder 0498A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Heritage Foundation - Contributions, 1947-1957 (Box 50, Folder 499)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $30,000 toward Freedom Train, $10,000 toward "vote" campaign of 1952. John D. Rockefeller 3rd gave $15,000 toward 1952 campaign and contributions to Crusade for Freedom. Contributions to 1956 "vote" campaign.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Heritage Foundation - Contributions, 1947-1957 (Box 50, Folder 0499A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Philosophical Society, 1931-1959 (Box 50, Folder 500)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. an inactive life member. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169Am5
  - Organizations and Parks - American Philosophical Society, 1931-1959 (Box 50, Folder 0500A)
    David Rockefeller became member, 1959. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Olympic Association, 1920-1950 (Box 50, Folder 501)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s 1924 conditional gift not completed; 1931 gift for winter games. Contributions to later games by Rockefeller Brothers Fund, Abby Rockefeller Mauze. Laurance S. Rockefeller served on 1960 New York City Committee. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauze.
    169Am6
  - Organizations and Parks - American Olympic Association, 1920-1950 (Box 50, Folder 0501A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Olympic Association, 1952-1961 (Box 50, Folder 502)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Olympic Association, 1952-1961 (Box 50, Folder 0502A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Olympic Association - Contributions, 1912-1931 (Box 50, Folder 503)
    By John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Olympic Association - United States Equestrian Team, 1951-1959 (Box 50, Folder 504)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $500 in 1951.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Provident Society, 1930-1945 (Box 50, Folder 505)
    Thrift-teaching organization's appeals all declined, except for one Nelson A. Rockefeller 1944 gift of $250. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    169Am61
  - Organizations and Parks - American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society, 1900-1960 (Box 51, Folder 506)
    John D. Rockefeller gave toward preservation of Stoney Point, 1902; Society interested in Palisades problem, 1900; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined active interest in Society. Invitations, reports on Society's activities. 1957 award to Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    169Am7
  - Organizations and Parks - American Friends Service Committee, 1932-1952 (Box 51, Folder 507)
    Appeals for aid for Quaker work in European relief before, during, and after World War II. Plans for relief work in Russia, 1947. Relief work with Arabs in Palestine. John D. Rockefeller 3rd pledge for purchase of house near United Nations. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, Rufus Jones.
    169Am8
  - Organizations and Parks - American Friends Service Committee, 1953-1960 (Box 51, Folder 508)
  - Organizations and Parks - American Friends Service Committee - Japanese Relocation Centers, 1942-1943 (Box 51, Folder 509)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd contribution to assist Nisei students; other appeals declined.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Friends Service Committee - German Rehabilitation - John J. McCloy, 1950-1951 (Box 51, Folder 510)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made funds available to John J. McCloy for work with German youth.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Friends Service Committee - Civilian Public Service Program, 1944-1946 (Box 51, Folder 511)
    Conscientious objector program; no Rockefeller interest.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Friends Service Committee - National Union for Fight Against Illiteracy, 1951-1952 (Box 51, Folder 512)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd contribution for educational work in Southern Italy.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Friends Service Committee - Contributions, 1932-1961 (Box 51, Folder 513)
    By various members of the family.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Society of Landscape Architects, 1938-1939, 1960 (Box 52, Folder 514)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. elected an honorary member because of Williamsburg work; no active participation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169Am9
  - Organizations and Parks - American Epilepsy League, Inc., 1945-1961 (Box 52, Folder 515)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd gift, 1946; later appeals declined. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    169Am10
  - Organizations and Parks - American Shore and Beach Preservation Association, 1946-1961 (Box 52, Folder 516)
    Aims of organization; Laurance S. Rockefeller interest. Correspondents include J. S. Smith, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    169Am11
  - Organizations and Parks - American Shore and Beach Preservation Association - Contributions, 1946-1957 (Box 52, Folder 517)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller was sponsoring member #1; his annual contributions; final contribution in 1957.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Russian Institute, 1942-1947 (Box 52, Folder 518)
    Suspicion of communist infiltration into Institute; Arthur W. Packard analysis. Appeals for aid declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard.
    169Am12
  - Organizations and Parks - American Committee for Restoration of Italian Monuments, Inc., 1948 (Box 52, Folder 519)
    Request for contributions to aid in post-war work on Italian art treasures in museums declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169Am13
  - Organizations and Parks - America-Italy Society, Inc., 1949-1961 (Box 52, Folder 520)
    Winthrop Aldrich was president; no real Rockefeller interest. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Winthrop Aldrich.
    169Am14
  - Organizations and Parks - America-Italy Society, Inc., 1949-1961 (Box 52, Folder 0520A)
    David Rockefeller contribution. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - American Foundation for the Study of Man, 1949 (Box 52, Folder 521)
    Unsuccessful attempts to get John D. Rockefeller 3rd to contribute to archeological expedition in Near East. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Wendell Phillips, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    169Am15
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Scandinavian Foundation, 1939-1961 (Box 52, Folder 522)
    Appeals and invitations declined until 1960, when Nelson A. Rockefeller gave $5,000. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    169Am16
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Scandinavian Foundation, 1939-1961 (Box 52, Folder 522A)
    Conditions Governing Access
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Korean Foundation, 1952-1954 (Box 52, Folder 523)
    Foundation engaged in relief work, but cultural exchange was its fundamental aim. Nelson A. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd declined to take leadership role in Foundation. In 1952, John D. Rockefeller 3rd gave $20,000. Gift by Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Most appeals declined after 1956. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Milton Eisenhower.
    169Am17
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Korean Foundation, 1952-1954 (Box 52, Folder 0523A)
    In 1953, David Rockefeller became trustee; he resigned in 1956. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Korean Foundation, 1954-1961 (Box 53, Folder 524)
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Korean Foundation, 1954-1961 (Box 53, Folder 0524A)
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Turkish Society, 1949-1954 (Box 53, Folder 525)
    Unsuccessful attempts to interest office in Society's work. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
    169Am18
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Japan Society, 1951-1958 (Box 53, Folder 526)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd interest in Society's work; his speech in Tokyo, 1952. J. J. McCloy's speech in Tokyo, 1958. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Douglas Overton.
    169Am19
  - Organizations and Parks - American-Japan Society - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Address, March 9, 1959 (Box 53, Folder 527)
    Speech made in Tokyo on American-Japanese understanding.
  - Organizations and Parks - Arctic Institute of North America, 1950-1956 (Box 53, Folder 528)
    Appeal for aid declined. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, R. C. Bates.
    169Ar
  - Organizations and Parks - Association for State and Local History, 1945-1961 (Box 53, Folder 529)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller contribution to aid in initiation of new program; Merit Award to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for his restoration work. Correspondents include Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    169As
  - Organizations and Parks - Association for State and Local History - "American Heritage", 1949-1956 (Box 53, Folder 530)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd gave to initial costs of magazine. Change in magazine to commercial hard-cover issue. No Rockefeller interest.
  - Organizations and Parks - Association of Community Chests and Councils, 1927-1934 (Box 53, Folder 531)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $5,000 toward study of corporation responsibility for Community Welfare Service, 1929.
  - Organizations and Parks - Austen Riggs Foundation, Inc., 1947-1960 (Box 53, Folder 532)
    Organized to train psychiatrists and provide free psychiatric care. Laurance S. Rockefeller contributions, substantial Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributions. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur Jones.
    169Au
  - Organizations and Parks - Austen Riggs Foundation, Inc., 1947-1960 (Box 53, Folder 0532A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Brookings Institution, 1933-1961 (Box 54, Folder 533)